[Music]
in the year 2000 a new human hormone was
discovered it was the 21st documented
fibroblast growth factor so they called
it fgf21
since this discovery fgf21 has emerged
as a key agent for promotion of
metabolic and artery health leanness and
longevity injected into fat monkeys and
they lose body weight without reducing
food intake and not just a little a 27
drop in body fat eating the same amount
in mice it increases their lifespan 30
to 40 comparable to lifelong caloric
restriction but again was achieved
without decreasing food intake the
researchers conclude that fgf21 could
potentially be used as a hormone therapy
to extend lifespan in mammals which has
gotten a big pharma salivating raising
the question can aging be drugged
and that's not all it can do the idea
that one drug can treat obesity diabetes
dyslipidemia like high cholesterol and
hypertension all at once might have
seemed impossible a few years ago but is
now a tantalizing and exciting prospect
the reason you can't just give people
straight fgf21 is that it gets rapidly
broken down in the body so you'd have to
get injections like every hour or two
around the clock so drug companies try
to patent a variety of longer acting
fgf21 lookalikes and indeed give people
a little pf052 31 0 23 and they can
lose about 10 pounds in 25 days along
with dramatic drops in triglycerides and
cholesterol
but then the side effects of these
newfangled drugs started cropping up
oh okay so hey what about this we
package the fgf21 gene into a virus and
then inject the virus and have a like
stitch extra fgf21 genes into our dna
or
you can just lace on your running shoes
right exercise boost fgf21 levels
which may in fact be one of the reasons
exercise is so good for us
which works better though aerobic
exercise eight weeks of running training
or resistance exercise eight weeks of
weights the answer is
both but the resistance exercise edged
out the running a 42 increase in fgf21
versus a 25 increase in the aerobic
exercise group
okay but what can we do with food yeah
you could try engineering and injecting
it but wouldn't it be easier to just
stimulate our own endogenous natural
production through diet
one way is through
no diet at all you may have noticed it's
been dubbed the starvation hormone
that's because fasting induces fgf21
but not just a day or two
physiologically fgf21 expression is
markedly increased in response to
fasting starvation but unlike mice which
show an increase after just six hours of
fasting humans don't get a notable surge
in fgf-21 until after a week right
fasting can quadruple after you have 21
but it takes 10 days of fasting which is
you know the very poster child of an
unsustainable eating pattern so how can
you get the benefits without the
starvation might a ketogenic diet be
able to mimic the fast
nope keto diets don't work in fact keep
it up for a few months you can actually
get a significant decline in levels
high fat diets may even interfere with
the boost you get from exercise
scene here in a study of high-intensity
interval training
what kind of diet does work then
we'll find out
next
[Music]
you